<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects | Academic</title>
    <link>/project/</link>
      <atom:link href="/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Projects</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 18 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/media/icon_hua2ec155b4296a9c9791d015323e16eb5_11927_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>/project/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Visualizing and quantifying topics on Twitter</title>
      <link>/project/twitter_sentiment_tracking/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/twitter_sentiment_tracking/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;using-osint-tools-and-transformers-to-extract-topics-and-sentiment&#34;&gt;Using OSINT tools and Transformers to extract topics and sentiment&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using the Blattodea tool that I helped develop during a hackathon, I retrieved the most recent tweets from Elon Musk. I then used one of &lt;a href=&#34;https://huggingface.co/models&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;HuggingFace&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a&gt; pre-trained sentiment classification models and &lt;a href=&#34;https://maartengr.github.io/BERTopic/index.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;BERTopic&lt;/a&gt; to extract and visualize key themes.
I have also developed an RShiny dashboard for this project to hone my interactive visualization skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Dashboard screenshot&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /project/twitter_sentiment_tracking/fig/dash_screenshot_hu7c0338f64b56aad8b96fcf4e43899430_140612_66a23c97d2bd90a9bd9aa98aedfa22f3.webp 400w,
               /project/twitter_sentiment_tracking/fig/dash_screenshot_hu7c0338f64b56aad8b96fcf4e43899430_140612_85f1f8c082af3f4339824fb7133c71d7.webp 760w,
               /project/twitter_sentiment_tracking/fig/dash_screenshot_hu7c0338f64b56aad8b96fcf4e43899430_140612_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;/project/twitter_sentiment_tracking/fig/dash_screenshot_hu7c0338f64b56aad8b96fcf4e43899430_140612_66a23c97d2bd90a9bd9aa98aedfa22f3.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;536&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;note-on-utility-and-future-projects&#34;&gt;Note on utility and future projects&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BERTopic can accommodate &lt;a href=&#34;https://maartengr.github.io/BERTopic/getting_started/online/online.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;online topic modelling&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; (i.e. incrementally adjusts topics with new data), and the results in this project have shown the model to be qualitatively coherent (lacking a labelled dataset, I am unable to compute the exact accuracy of clustering/classification). It would not be difficult to expand this work to a more regular, (semi-)automated pipeline to &lt;em&gt;monitor social media content&lt;/em&gt; around a particular hashtag/person/theme and to extract insight or detect sudden changes. Suppose you were a news organisation looking to gauge interest in a particular recent event. Although social media isn&amp;rsquo;t representative of general discourse around any given topic, taking data from Twitter, passing it through BERTopic and then setting the pipeline to regularly update the data and topics, would give you the data to assess at least some of the discussion around a theme or event.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;results-and-thoughts&#34;&gt;Results and thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Results are analysed and visualized at greater length inside the repo&amp;rsquo;s index.Rmarkdown notebook. For cleaning, EDA and modelling code, please see the Jupyter notebooks in the repo, explained in the filing system below)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;overall-usage&#34;&gt;Overall usage&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been able to extract clear and definite topics from the collected data, and the pattern of activity around key themes has been what I expected it to be. For example, Musk&amp;rsquo;s opining on ending the war in Ukraine generated a larger amount of responses across the board than his other tweets. Through this project I&amp;rsquo;ve found that BERTopic has been extremely useful and capable of extracting information from unstructured text data, and I plan on using it in future projects. Moreover, the model was able to group topic clusters at a greater level of precision and accuracy than I had honestly expected. In the dendrogram included below I show how some of the topics (the most interesting ones) have been grouped by the model and what the model tells us vs what we can infer. For an NLP project is arguably even more important than in most data science projects to combine contextual knowledge and data viz with the results: language is far more ambiguous and mysterious than numbers.
Note that the tweets analysed here are all from 1st August 2022 onwards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;clustering-topics&#34;&gt;Clustering Topics&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given the time-range for our data, it should be no surprise that tweets about the war have formed their own distinct group of clusters. It&amp;rsquo;s easy to see how topics 35, 36, 1 and 10 are linked. For interpreting this graph, recall that the most important number to count is the number of steps to take along the tree for two topics/leafs to connect.
(Note that these are graphs generated with the help of BERTopic and there&amp;rsquo;s far less you can do in terms of graph customization).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Hierarchy of our topics of interest&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /project/twitter_sentiment_tracking/fig/hierarchical_select_top_hu70c2815d607fc6af5045f54f172892cf_68184_cdc00f0f301053cdfb0b5bf7aef0b408.webp 400w,
               /project/twitter_sentiment_tracking/fig/hierarchical_select_top_hu70c2815d607fc6af5045f54f172892cf_68184_68c54f40c6fb247aa0c0d1791a7c91ed.webp 760w,
               /project/twitter_sentiment_tracking/fig/hierarchical_select_top_hu70c2815d607fc6af5045f54f172892cf_68184_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;/project/twitter_sentiment_tracking/fig/hierarchical_select_top_hu70c2815d607fc6af5045f54f172892cf_68184_cdc00f0f301053cdfb0b5bf7aef0b408.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;357&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Topics 29 and 9 form an understandable cluster together as there were a significant number of tweets focused on Starlink&amp;rsquo;s activity in Ukraine (and its commercial activity more generally), both by Musk and his followers.
The grouping of clusters 3 and 2 is more interesting: closer inspection of 2 revealed that it includes some tweets related to Twitter bots (something Musk has made a point of discussing openly recently), which would link it sensibly to topic 3; however some of the tweets were also referring to Tesla &amp;lsquo;bots&amp;rsquo; (i.e. Tesla&amp;rsquo;s robotics research and department). If we&amp;rsquo;d had a set of topic labels for each of these, it&amp;rsquo;s very likely that BERTopic would misclassify the tweets in this particular topic. Topic two tweets range from :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;| &amp;ldquo;Tesla Bot is the future of robotics 🤯 &amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;to&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;| &amp;ldquo;If Twitter put as much effort into botspam removal as they do into subpoenas we wouldnt have this problem in the first place&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Human language users like us can tell that these are two distinct themes. Yet I&amp;rsquo;d say that this amalgamation of is quite an understandable mistake, given the amount of words that appear across topic 2 that make it strongly related to topic 3 and others. It is possible that if we had more documents, BERTopic would&amp;rsquo;ve split topic 2 into another leaf.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Towards the bottom we can also see three topics that, although not as closely aligned as the war-themed ones, still cluster together. These are all connected by the theme of rocketry, SpaceX and all of Musk&amp;rsquo;s space-related endeavours. It&amp;rsquo;s encouraging to see that the model was able to place these closely together. Note the next leaf that joins this particular sub-branch, topic 55, related to engines. Now, when I originally looked at this topic, I figured that the algorithm had misgrouped again and that discussions of engines must be focussed on cars. However, I was wrong and the algo was right - inspection of the tweets with this as their main topic (currently topic nr 48 in our merged data) revealed that my intuition was wrong:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;| &amp;ldquo;Hi Elon  😀 According to  380 tankers delivered to Starbase So I would be really happy to know Will B7 performs a long duration full stack 33 engines static fire Thanks🙏😀&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;| &amp;ldquo;How certain are you on the final number of engines for Superheavy Booster&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and, a slight outlier in some sense:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;| &amp;ldquo;there will be a day when there are literally 69 boosters 🤓&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(I do enjoy points of childish levity in a dataset.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Anyway&lt;/em&gt;, this is another great example of BERTopic&amp;rsquo;s strengths as a model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;twitter-stats-over-time&#34;&gt;Twitter stats over time&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we take a look at the by-day total likes, re-tweets and responses, it&amp;rsquo;s clear that 3rd Oct 2022, when Musk posted his poll on the war, was a bit of watershed in terms of twitter stats (note that the ones in the plot are scaled down for comparison&amp;rsquo;s sake- he didn&amp;rsquo;t just get under 5 responses!). This particular day certainly generated the most conversation (if we take number of responses as a proxy) and in generally most of his tweet stats increased somewhat in the period after. Apart from the one-day spike, it can hardly be said that the furore many felt as a result of the 3rd Oct twitter poll has manifested at the tweet meta-data level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Stats for Musk&amp;amp;rsquo;s tweets over time&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /project/twitter_sentiment_tracking/fig/ggplot_musk_all_total_tweets_feats_hu3ba6f4586ae26ee2ba8466bf160ced7b_282186_df48baed456d29cace13c80db6489c6b.webp 400w,
               /project/twitter_sentiment_tracking/fig/ggplot_musk_all_total_tweets_feats_hu3ba6f4586ae26ee2ba8466bf160ced7b_282186_e05b136ea41cef6c84108e220707709a.webp 760w,
               /project/twitter_sentiment_tracking/fig/ggplot_musk_all_total_tweets_feats_hu3ba6f4586ae26ee2ba8466bf160ced7b_282186_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;/project/twitter_sentiment_tracking/fig/ggplot_musk_all_total_tweets_feats_hu3ba6f4586ae26ee2ba8466bf160ced7b_282186_df48baed456d29cace13c80db6489c6b.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;543&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we compare &lt;em&gt;average&lt;/em&gt; values before and after the poll went out (shown below with the box and jitter plot- each point represents one tweet), then we see barely any changes at all. The distribution of retweets and responses seems to be somewhat more skewed, but looking at it it&amp;rsquo;s not even worth doing a statistical test.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;EDA_twitter_sentiment_tracking/boxplot_before_and_after.png&#34; alt=&#34;Stats for Musk&amp;amp;rsquo;s tweets before and after&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How about when we combine tweet stats with the topics, just for Elon Musk&amp;rsquo;s tweets? Well, the heatmap below shows that there isn&amp;rsquo;t much correlation between the probability scores of each of our main topics of interest and any of the three tweet features:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;EDA_twitter_sentiment_tracking/corr_heatmap.png&#34; alt=&#34;Correlation heatmap of main topics and tweet stats&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two correlations worth testing for here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;nr of likes and tweets on SpaceX&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;nr of responses and tweets on Russia-Ukraine war&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s check them for statistical significance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;| H0: there is no statistically significant correlation between our determined* cluster of Elon Musk&amp;rsquo;s tweets on the Russia-Ukraine war and the number of responses to his tweets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;| H1: there is a statistically significant correlation between our determined* Elon Musk&amp;rsquo;s tweets on the Russia-Ukraine war and the number of responses to his tweets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Setting alpha = 0.05/(number of tests) = 0.025&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;| H0: there is no statistically significant correlation between our determined* cluster of Elon Musk&amp;rsquo;s tweets on SpaceX and the number of likes to these tweets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;| H1: there is a statistically significant correlation between our determined* Elon Musk&amp;rsquo;s tweets on SpaceX and the number of likes to these tweets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Setting alpha = 0.05/(number of tests) = 0.025&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;*I&amp;rsquo;m referring to them as determined by us because these tweets were categorised via a semi-supervised method, and they are not a gold-standard dataset that has been hand-labelled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;sentiment-and-topics&#34;&gt;Sentiment and Topics&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was interested to see how different topics within this data in terms of the sentiment. To that end, I passed the tweets through a pre-trained sentiment classifier to infer whether they were positive or negative. Below I show how this varies over time for the Tweets directly mentioning Elon Musk:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Sentiment around Musk by topic&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /project/twitter_sentiment_tracking/fig/ggplot_pct_tweets_by_topic_and_sentiment_hub766bd4ccc75a0dda2f3385562008020_455449_5fd6e367845b11c845a000c67d512f55.webp 400w,
               /project/twitter_sentiment_tracking/fig/ggplot_pct_tweets_by_topic_and_sentiment_hub766bd4ccc75a0dda2f3385562008020_455449_90c48b09a35b4ca2367466a217ef5f56.webp 760w,
               /project/twitter_sentiment_tracking/fig/ggplot_pct_tweets_by_topic_and_sentiment_hub766bd4ccc75a0dda2f3385562008020_455449_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;/project/twitter_sentiment_tracking/fig/ggplot_pct_tweets_by_topic_and_sentiment_hub766bd4ccc75a0dda2f3385562008020_455449_5fd6e367845b11c845a000c67d512f55.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;543&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s important to note that the amount of tweets is hard to include in the graph and the y-axis reports on percentages by day. Prior to early autumn &amp;lsquo;22, the number of tweets mentioning Elon and concerned with the war was significantly lower. Note that although there is a trend line included, it wherever the green and red lines run tangentially to each other near 100% is to be ignored: those are days with very few datapoints and where the % sentiment per day flips between fully positive and fully negative easily.
I&amp;rsquo;ve tried to represent the number of tweets in the opacity/transparency of the points, however, that is skewed by the fact the outlier of negative tweets Musk received the around the time he released his poll. Nevertheless, at least within this limited subset of his audience, there appears to have been a clear rise in the proportion of negative tweets, especially around the theme of the war. However, this batch is not representative of course: partially for the reason stated earlier about how the data was collect but also because these topics do not cover the full range of sentiment around Musk. Consider the fact that there could easily have been someone tweeting &amp;ldquo;@elonmusk, please stay out of global affairs&amp;rdquo; and this would likely not have been categoriesed as part of the war-theme topic cluster. Therefore, we are very likely undercounting. Realistically, here are only looking at the subset of tweets that were in some way in Elon&amp;rsquo;s extended network, that mentioned him and that mentioned terms directly relevant to the war, so that someone with no prior knowledge could have picked them up and said &amp;ldquo;yes, this Tweet has X opinion about Musk on this topic&amp;rdquo;. Lastly, there is the possibility of tweets that mention Musk but without actually being focussed on him: e.g. someone making a negative statement about the war in general and @ Musk in it for different reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the opacity of the points should be a greater focus of attention: it would appear that attention flared up dramatically on Musk (for this segment of the data) and then died down again slowly, but maintained the tendency to be negative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;bottom-line&#34;&gt;Bottom-line&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Musk&amp;rsquo;s tweets on the war did generate a significant response on Twitter, although this appears to have been short-lived&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;These tweets form very clear clusters of topics and can be amalgamated with other, tangentially related topics.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;BERTopic is an awesome tool that I&amp;rsquo;m looking forward to using again!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;repo-filing-system&#34;&gt;Repo filing system:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notebooks&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;index.md - principal file of findings and final results; most relevant notebook to most people
2a. Topic_modelling_with_BERT.ipynb - notebook details the journey of analysing the model results and extracting insights.
2b. Modelling_w_BERTopic_GColab.ipynb - Google Colab notebook where the BERTopic and sentiment models&amp;rsquo; results were generated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;EDA.ipynb - rough exploration of the data; go here for more in-depth look at some of the data. Most of the visualizations therein were not used.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;data_cleaning.ipynb - notebook detailing the entire cleaning process. Primarily relies on py modules within functions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Folders&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;data - folder containing raw, processed, clean and feature data and any additional summary data generated. Also contains inferred data (i.e. tweets and their predicted sentiment; tweets and their associated topics)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;models - the fitted BERTopic model files - &lt;strong&gt;NOTE&lt;/strong&gt; unfortunately, due to a bug in the way the models were saved, it is not possible to load them up locally on a lot of machines. However, it is possible to reproduce their creation and fitting on Google Colab, using the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/Ioana-P/IoanaFio/blob/main/content/project/twitter_sentiment_tracking/Modelling_w_BERTopic_GColab.ipynb&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Colab notebook&lt;/a&gt; inside this repo
*fig - all data viz (including interactive HTML files)
*functions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;archive - any additional files and subfolders will be here&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;References:
@article{grootendorst2022bertopic,
title={BERTopic: Neural topic modeling with a class-based TF-IDF procedure},
author={Grootendorst, Maarten},
journal={arXiv preprint arXiv:2203.05794},
year={2022}
}&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sentiment Analysis with Pytorch</title>
      <link>/project/sentiment-analysis-modelling-with-pytorch/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/sentiment-analysis-modelling-with-pytorch/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;sentiment-analysis-in-pytorch&#34;&gt;Sentiment Analysis in Pytorch&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Training and deploying a Sentiment Analysis model in Pytorch using AWS Sagemaker. The data used was IMDB&amp;rsquo;s Movie review dataset (&lt;a href=&#34;https://ai.stanford.edu/~amaas/data/sentiment/%29&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://ai.stanford.edu/~amaas/data/sentiment/)&lt;/a&gt;, which consists of 50,000 instances of binary labelled movie reviews.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;how-do-we-take-a-machine-learning-model-and-put-it-out-there-to-be-used&#34;&gt;How do we take a machine learning model and put it out there to be used?&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;how-do-we-deploy-an-inference-model-out-there-in-the-real-world-to-interact-with-a-user&#34;&gt;How do we deploy an inference model out there in the real world, to interact with a user?&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amazon Web Services platform allows us to train, host and deploy a variety of models that we can use to gain insight from user data. For this instance, suppose we are looking to gauge opinions on a recent product, a film, a game, a trailer, etc.. Users might express their views via some form of text data (e.g. Tweets, reviews, Facebook posts, reddit comments). A deployed sentiment analysis model would be used to take in that data and infer the polarity of the data (positive or negative) and return to us, the number of positive and negative reviews respectively. This would be helpful to inform future product-related or marketing decisions regarding whatever product we&amp;rsquo;re putting out there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My foci for this project were a) developing my &lt;strong&gt;understanding of successful model deployment on AWS Sagemaker&lt;/strong&gt; and b) practicing writing a &lt;strong&gt;neural network model in pytorch&lt;/strong&gt; and the appropriate data preprocessing functions for it. Given that this is a widely-used, canonical dataset, model performance was less of a priority. To that end I&amp;rsquo;m including below a flow-chart of the architecture (Figure 1) - to follow the logic of what happens to a user&amp;rsquo;s inputted review, start from the top left (&amp;ldquo;User&amp;rsquo;s review&amp;rdquo;) and follow the arrows to the right.
I&amp;rsquo;ve included the training phase in the same diagram as deployment but it should be noted that training - shown through the righthand part of the diagram (labelled training data fed into the Sagemaker model and then stored in S3 buckets) - happens &lt;em&gt;prior&lt;/em&gt; to deployment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;flow-chart&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /project/sentiment-analysis-modelling-with-pytorch/fig/sentiment_analysis_aws_flow_hu1d99e222f3b6a766d72cf462d1c736fd_128671_6be9b60775e3bb77510e7c528d4fbd3d.webp 400w,
               /project/sentiment-analysis-modelling-with-pytorch/fig/sentiment_analysis_aws_flow_hu1d99e222f3b6a766d72cf462d1c736fd_128671_74dd00a16cbf37242ef27e9739defb88.webp 760w,
               /project/sentiment-analysis-modelling-with-pytorch/fig/sentiment_analysis_aws_flow_hu1d99e222f3b6a766d72cf462d1c736fd_128671_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;/project/sentiment-analysis-modelling-with-pytorch/fig/sentiment_analysis_aws_flow_hu1d99e222f3b6a766d72cf462d1c736fd_128671_6be9b60775e3bb77510e7c528d4fbd3d.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;580&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fig 1 - Flow-chart showing how a Sagemaker notebook instance containing a Pytorch model interacts with an API, Lambda function and webapp&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Model performance and issues are supervised through AWS&amp;rsquo; CloudWatch platform, which provides a chronological log of activity from the model endpoint.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A basic webapp, API and Lambda function were written for this project as well but are non-functioning as having these hosted on Sagemaker incurs significant costs. If you&amp;rsquo;re interested in replicating the project, the code here was tested while the S3 buckets and notebooks were still fully functioning so everything should run if cloned to a Sagemaker notebook instance perfectly, asuming all files are copied over. If you&amp;rsquo;re curious to see what the final, user-facing product would look like, there are some examples in Figures 2 and 3:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;pos&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /project/sentiment-analysis-modelling-with-pytorch/fig/pos_huf342677c58750bdb400499c29a8920a2_112513_69b4e4246a866ba350815cb2312f2fda.webp 400w,
               /project/sentiment-analysis-modelling-with-pytorch/fig/pos_huf342677c58750bdb400499c29a8920a2_112513_287d5862b4078660187f115c76a4ee85.webp 760w,
               /project/sentiment-analysis-modelling-with-pytorch/fig/pos_huf342677c58750bdb400499c29a8920a2_112513_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;/project/sentiment-analysis-modelling-with-pytorch/fig/pos_huf342677c58750bdb400499c29a8920a2_112513_69b4e4246a866ba350815cb2312f2fda.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;254&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

Fig 2 - quite pleased that the model got past the sneakily positive adjectives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;neg&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /project/sentiment-analysis-modelling-with-pytorch/fig/neg_hueaf939b9d0ded4bcadfadb59be3286f0_85586_46cff1ec5735d847a05bdb685b051a41.webp 400w,
               /project/sentiment-analysis-modelling-with-pytorch/fig/neg_hueaf939b9d0ded4bcadfadb59be3286f0_85586_d0b68549bfa5126ddb72a5c31198fa32.webp 760w,
               /project/sentiment-analysis-modelling-with-pytorch/fig/neg_hueaf939b9d0ded4bcadfadb59be3286f0_85586_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;/project/sentiment-analysis-modelling-with-pytorch/fig/neg_hueaf939b9d0ded4bcadfadb59be3286f0_85586_46cff1ec5735d847a05bdb685b051a41.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;381&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

Fig 3 - also pleased that this model seems to have taste&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Navigation:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SageMaker Project.ipynb - main sagemaker notebook; contains more detailed and thorrough notes and comments on how the model is built and how the various components of AWS interact with each other&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;website - directory containing webapp html code&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;serve - directory with necessary deployment .py files:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;model.py - model training functions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;predict.py - model deployment and inference functions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;utils.py - preprocessing functions for text data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;train - directory with additional model training files:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;requirements.txt - files needed by AWS for model to run&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;dict_data - directory containing word_dict.pkl - dictionary of unique integer to word key-value pairs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A significant amount of the material for this project was learned through Udacity&amp;rsquo;s Machine Learning Engineer Nanodegree. I am grateful for their content and resources and recommend the course.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;References:
Data -
Andrew L. Maas, Raymond E. Daly, Peter T. Pham, Dan Huang, Andrew Y. Ng, and Christopher Potts. (2011). Learning Word Vectors for Sentiment Analysis. The 49th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL 2011).
Pytorch - &lt;a href=&#34;https://pytorch.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://pytorch.org/&lt;/a&gt;
If you&amp;rsquo;re interested in learning how to use Pytorch, they provide a variety of great tutorials at &lt;a href=&#34;https://pytorch.org/tutorials/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://pytorch.org/tutorials/&lt;/a&gt;
Udacity - &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.udacity.com/course/machine-learning-engineer-nanodegree--nd009t&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.udacity.com/course/machine-learning-engineer-nanodegree--nd009t&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Analysing scraped job data</title>
      <link>/project/job-market-exploration/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/job-market-exploration/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;exploring-the-uk-data-science-job-market-through-indeed-job-posts&#34;&gt;Exploring the UK Data Science job market through Indeed job posts&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I scraped 1082 job posts from Indeed.co.uk, searching for 3 different types of data science roles via the title, and then analysed the data. Please bear in mind that all the data was off one site only (I hope to be able to get job data off LinkedIn/Glassdoor at some point in the future) in late Nov 2020.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bear in mind that this is an &lt;strong&gt;exploratory project&lt;/strong&gt; - findings should be taken with a pinch of salt, and really the results need to be corroborated with a ~~replication of the project in 2021 or with other research. ~~
Update 01/06/2022:
The scraping code has been updated again and tested on a small sample (n=10) of jobs with the search term title:(data,scientist).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Location is now taken directly from the search results page, which seems to be returning more locations than the alternative as it is a more easily identifiable element&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Retrieve&amp;rdquo; has been removed from the GUI options. This was originally intended for the purpose of retrieving historical data from an SQLite db, but I&amp;rsquo;ve mothballed that idea now since it didn&amp;rsquo;t give enough clear benefits.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;findings&#34;&gt;Findings&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most Data Science jobs do not advertise their salary openly (only 41.5% do)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The median Data Science salary is about £45k; the mean is about £51k&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The majority of roles are based in London&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The median Data Analyst role is under £40k, whereas the median Data Scientist and Machine Learning jobs are above £60k. Roles with &amp;ldquo;Scientist&amp;rdquo; and/or &amp;ldquo;Machine learning&amp;rdquo; earn £20k more (&lt;strong&gt;on average&lt;/strong&gt;) than roles with &amp;ldquo;Analyst&amp;rdquo; in the title.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /project/job-market-exploration/fig/salaries_all_hu4969e48710dd2b978bb8969624a5a666_60594_27646ab952fe057815f2a6bea464f4e6.webp 400w,
               /project/job-market-exploration/fig/salaries_all_hu4969e48710dd2b978bb8969624a5a666_60594_defd3dd196499dbe35ac06cadd96b836.webp 760w,
               /project/job-market-exploration/fig/salaries_all_hu4969e48710dd2b978bb8969624a5a666_60594_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;/project/job-market-exploration/fig/salaries_all_hu4969e48710dd2b978bb8969624a5a666_60594_27646ab952fe057815f2a6bea464f4e6.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;691&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;5&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;London and Cambridge have the highest average salaries; the former has the widest spread of salaries&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re a median-salary London Data Analyst, you&amp;rsquo;re getting paid as well as the median salary for all Data Science roles outside the company.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Just over 14% of overall roles are looking for a &amp;ldquo;Senior&amp;rdquo; hire. Less than 2% explicitly advertise for a &amp;lsquo;Junior&amp;rsquo; hire.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The most popular languages / skills (based on our search) were: Python, SQL, R, AWS and Azure (in decreasing order of mentions).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /project/job-market-exploration/fig/percentage_mentions_by_group_hu8d36c2c10dd8a064e7a3b8b5c94791ad_148193_7d786cb87c2eec60085c33d40a11c0ee.webp 400w,
               /project/job-market-exploration/fig/percentage_mentions_by_group_hu8d36c2c10dd8a064e7a3b8b5c94791ad_148193_c4bf678cc770ffdfe0583142c80b396b.webp 760w,
               /project/job-market-exploration/fig/percentage_mentions_by_group_hu8d36c2c10dd8a064e7a3b8b5c94791ad_148193_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;/project/job-market-exploration/fig/percentage_mentions_by_group_hu8d36c2c10dd8a064e7a3b8b5c94791ad_148193_7d786cb87c2eec60085c33d40a11c0ee.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;365&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;9&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using feature engineering and 3 different iterations of models, I was not able to predict salary from job description and title data. This indicates that either more data is needed (likely since there only 274 data points in the training data) or that it&amp;rsquo;s not possible to reliably predict the salary from such data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There was insufficient data to determine if years of experience required / requested correlated with annual salary.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;After using topic modelling, a few topics stood out - most noticeably the &lt;code&gt;Academic_&amp;amp;_Research&lt;/code&gt; topic which seems to be the only one that has a moderate correlation with salary.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Full method and implementation in notebook - Data_Scientist_UK_Q4_Job_market_analysis.ipynb&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;future-steps&#34;&gt;Future Steps&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Improve webscraping process to pick up &amp;ldquo;Remote work&amp;rdquo; tags that may be stored sepately on the job website to the main text&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Collect more data in 2021 and reiterate project to test current findings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using feature engineering and regex, for future batches, determine subgroup of jobs that are research-focussed and test again if those roles do correlate with salary.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;repo-navigation&#34;&gt;Repo navigation:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;index.ipynb&lt;/strong&gt; - principal notebook; questions and project plan located there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;scrape_indeed_gui.py&lt;/strong&gt; - script for running Job Scraper Tool (built using pySimpleGui)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;archive/&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;cleaning.ipynb - notebook to check the outputs of the scraping tool&amp;rsquo;s results&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;untitled.ipynb - nb used to load and check extraneous data (e.g. ONS salary information for sector)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;clean_data/ - folder preprocessed data&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;raw_data/ folder including data as immediately outputed after webscraping stage&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;LDA_vis_plot.html - interactive visualisation of Latent Dirichlet Allocation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;functions.py - scripted functions and classes stored here, including webscraping tool&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;topic_mod.py - functions for topic modelling&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;fig/ - noteable visualisations saved here&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;references&#34;&gt;References:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SlashData Report - &amp;lsquo;State of the Developer Nation 19th Edition&amp;rsquo; - &lt;a href=&#34;https://slashdata-website-cms.s3.amazonaws.com/sample_reports/y7fzAZ8e5XuKCL1Q.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://slashdata-website-cms.s3.amazonaws.com/sample_reports/y7fzAZ8e5XuKCL1Q.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Logistic Ordinal Regression - &lt;a href=&#34;http://fa.bianp.net/blog/2013/logistic-ordinal-regression/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;http://fa.bianp.net/blog/2013/logistic-ordinal-regression/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;pyLDAvis Overview - &lt;a href=&#34;https://nbviewer.jupyter.org/github/bmabey/pyLDAvis/blob/master/notebooks/pyLDAvis_overview.ipynb&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://nbviewer.jupyter.org/github/bmabey/pyLDAvis/blob/master/notebooks/pyLDAvis_overview.ipynb&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;key-assumptions-to-bear-in-mind&#34;&gt;Key Assumptions to bear in mind:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data sourcing&lt;/strong&gt; - Data was sourced purely from Indeed.co.uk over a limited time span. The individual time of scraping is recorded for each job post inside the raw_data file raw_data/SE_jobs_20_11_2020.csv. Further sampling over time will be needed to replicate or falsify findings.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;National averages&lt;/strong&gt; - ONS data was filtered to retrieve data for 2019 as 2020 data is a. not fully available yet broken down by and b. 2020 survey data was affected by the Covid19 lockdown and the move to telephone polling. Although the 2019 mean salary is not a fair comparison for data retrieved in Q3 2020, it provides a rough benchmark against which we can compare our sample.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data mining&lt;/strong&gt; - The salary extraction method is reliant on the pattern finding of text that &amp;ldquo;looks like salary data&amp;rdquo; - i.e. the python script that I wrote searched specifically for text that included &amp;ldquo;£&amp;rdquo; followed by any length of numbers (continuous or punctuated by a comma) and a time period phrase such as &amp;ldquo;per day&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;per annum&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;a year&amp;rdquo;, etc. Spot-checking showed the method to be robust. Where a range was stated (e.g. &amp;ldquo;£40,000 - £50,000&amp;rdquo;) the mean was taken. The same applied to regex mining for programming languages: particular challenges were encountered where languages had many variants (JavaScript for instance) or even different spelling (Javascript) - I tried to capture as many as feasible in the regex patterns. It might seem strange that the values for C++ and C# came out near zero, but, after multiple rounds of testing, I still could not find any, even though my function searching for those two languages had specific conditions written to ensure that they were detected.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Webscraping process&lt;/strong&gt; - The webscraping tool generally managed to retrieve the maximum of 19 jobs posted per page on Indeed&amp;rsquo;s search result pages. The first part of the scraping had a human-in-the-loop (i.e. myself) monitoring the scraper navigating the page, to ensure data retrieval quality. Occasionally, due to an unforeseen pop-up or a nested html element, I had to scroll the automated Chrome browser in the right direction so that it would carry on retrieving new job post URLs. However, this means that some job posts may have been overlooked. This shouldn&amp;rsquo;t pose a significant problem, since I was sampling from the much larger number of total available job posts, but the sampling method&amp;rsquo;s randomness is reliant on the order in which Indeed presents results.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Searching by title&lt;/strong&gt; - since we&amp;rsquo;re relying on Indeed.co.uk&amp;rsquo;s internal search functions, I specifically chose to input the text &amp;ldquo;title:(software, developer)&amp;rdquo;- this would only bring up a job if it contained either or both of those 2 words in any order. This would allow as well for examples such as &amp;ldquo;Software &amp;amp; Architecture Developer&amp;rdquo; and other valid variations. I realise of course that this would exclude perfectly valid choices from our selection, but I decided to prioritise sample purity foremost.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
